Chapter 1: A Different Choice

Author's Notes: The start of this chapter is copied directly from LessWrong's "Harry Potter and the Methods of Rationality", chapter 81 (s/5782108/81/). The transition from LessWrong's words to my own is sharp, and is intended to pass unnoticed. I am merely exploring the consequences of one decision being made differently, and otherwise being as faithful as I can to LessWrong's story.

And Harry knew, then, as he looked at the red-golden bird, what he had to do as well. It should have been obvious from the beginning, that solution.

"Then I too will do what I must," Harry said up to Dumbledore, as though the two of them stood alone in the room. "You do realize that, don't you?"

The old wizard shook his trembling head. "You will change your mind when you are older -"

"I'm not talking about that," Harry said, his voice still strange in his own ears. "I mean that I will not allow Hermione Granger to be eaten by Dementors under any circumstances. Period. Regardless of what any law says, and no matter what I have to do to stop it. Do I still need to spell it out?"

A strange male voice spoke from somewhere far away, "Be sure that the girl is taken directly to Azkaban, and put under extra guard."

Harry waited, staring at the old wizard, and then spoke again. "I will go to Azkaban," Harry said to the old wizard, as though they stood alone in the world, "before Hermione can be taken there, and start snapping my fingers. It may cost me my life, but by the time she gets there, there won't be an Azkaban anymore."

Some members of the Wizengamot gasped in surprise.

Then a greater number started laughing.

"How would you even get there, little boy?" someone said, from among those who were laughing.

"I have my ways of going places," said the boy's distant voice. Harry kept his eyes on Dumbledore, on the old wizard staring at him in shock. Harry didn't look directly at Fawkes, didn't give his plan away; but in his mind he prepared to summon the phoenix to transport him, prepared to fill his mind with light and fury, to call for the fire-bird with all his might, he might have to do it upon the instant if Dumbledore pointed his wand -

"Would you truly?" the old wizard said to Harry, also as if the two of them stood alone in the room.

The room went silent again as everyone stared in shock at the Chief Warlock of the Wizengamot, who seemed to be taking the mad threat completely seriously.

The old wizard's eyes were locked only on Harry. "Would you risk everything - everything - only for her?"

"Yes," Harry said back in reply.

That's the wrong answer, you know, said Slytherin. Seriously.

But it's the true answer.

"You will not see reason?" said the old wizard.

"Apparently not," Harry said back.

The gazes stayed locked.

"This is terrible folly," said the old wizard.

"I am aware of this," answered the hero. "Now get out of my way."

Strange light glinted in the ancient blue eyes. "No, Harry Potter. I cannot allow you to go into debt to Lucius Malfoy, and I will not allow you to attack Azkaban. You will not be able to reach Azkaban as you intend; there are restraints of which you are unaware. I truly am sorry."

Harry stared at the old wizard, thinking desperately. So Fawkes was ruled out, probably by the same spell which prevented the bird of light from screaming at the Wizengamot. Harry had no further options – only an overwhelming but impotent desire to be in Azkaban. Hoping against hope, he turned to Fawkes anyway.

Fawkes stirred, but was restrained by whatever magic the wizards had placed on him. As he stirred, however, a patch of air near Harry's left hand flickered and another creature of living fire appeared, blazing brighter than Harry had ever seen of Fawkes.

Harry had only a split-second to react – the Hall at large was incoherent uproar, but Dumbledore was already pointing his wand and McGonagall was reaching for her own. As Harry tried to gather his wits, his left hand was already reaching towards the furious golden light; a moment later, boy and bird were gone.

Harry felt the wrongness the instant he flickered back into existence, knew it even through the phoenix-warmth suffusing his body. He knew where he was and why, even before his eyes registered the voids around him.

Beyond those voids, three blank stone walls loomed high above him. He noted fleetingly that his hole had been repaired. Far above him, the triangle of sky visible was an incongruously bright and untroubled blue. Beneath his feet was a soft powdery soil, akin to sifted ashes. Dozens of voids thronged around him, even as his fingers began a precise and well-rehearsed sequence of movements on his wand. He saw that the voids were retreating, driven away by the resolve which had summoned the phoenix. He wondered briefly whether they were also afraid of the phoenix, if "afraid" even made sense in describing Dementors. Then his fingers finished their complicated movements, and he brandished his wand. There was no need now to censor any thoughts; his thought was rejection of death, and this time he could open the floodgates and pour himself out and do it now.

"Expecto Patronum!"

The shining humanoid leapt from Harry's wand, unbearably bright within the instant. Harry turned away and closed his eyes, and in his mind he sank the wells deeper and deeper inside himself. In a sense he had forgotten that he was in Azkaban to destroy a finite number of Dementors; his task was to spend himself and destroy Death itself, and in that task there was no room for restraint or half-measures. Even turned away, even through closed eyelids, he felt the heat in his eyes as the incandescent inferno burned his life-force away.

The boy stood still, a tiny figure in a pose which would have looked dramatic in another time and place. Here and now it was a mere speck within the towering edifice of Azkaban, no more than a hint of a silhouette within the searing light of the absolute Patronus.

Far above, the iron calm of a hundred years shattered as Bahry One-Hand stared slack-jawed down into the Pit. He couldn't see the Patronus clearly or Harry at all, not at this distance, but he recognised Patronus light, and he couldn't begin to understand how it could be brighter than the midday sun above him. Turning his aching eyes away from the light, he missed the arrival of Fawkes the phoenix with Albus Dumbledore.

Fawkes had flickered into existence some 50 metres above the bottom of the pit, high enough to be clear of the Dementors. Dumbledore, suspended in mid-air by this bird on his shoulder, stared downward in shock and utter confusion – at first he saw only an impossible brightness of Patronus fire, bright like the heart of a nuclear explosion. It took a few seconds for his eyes to find Harry, that faint mote lost in the impossible silver fire. Then, even as Dumbledore discerned the faint shadow, the light flicked out so abruptly that his eyes saw only after-images and darkness.

As his sight cleared, Albus saw the tiny figure lying motionless in the dirt. He saw the wings of golden fire spread over the boy's face. Albus and Fawkes dropped rapidly, landing before the unmoving form of Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres.

With rapid sweeps of his dread wand, the old man cast a wordless flurry of charms to determine the boy's health: he was alive, thank Merlin, and apparently not harmed in any way beyond normal exhaustion. Despite a prolific career in magical research, despite much careful thought since the incident with the Dementor at Hogwarts, Albus Dumbledore still had absolutely no idea how a first-year could possibly wield (let alone invent) such potent magicks. Who was this child, that he could so abruptly destroy almost every Dementor in Magical Britain? And at that thought, his attention turned suddenly to the political implications - this would radically change the political realities in the Wizengamot and beyond, but how?

These calculations were interrupted by the Bahry One-Hand, voice steady once more as he brought his broomstick down to ground level. "What in Merlin's name just happened?"

"Ah, Bahry. It appears that Harry Potter has just destroyed every Dementor in Azkaban. And before you ask - no, I have not the faintest idea how."

"You can't be serious."

"Deadly serious, I'm afraid. He threatened it when his friend was sentenced to be sent here, and he seems to have carried out his threat. I tried to stop him, but I failed."

Bahry stared searchingly at Dumbledore for a long moment, then yanked the mirror off his belt.

"Mike, tell Director Bones that the Dementors are all gone. The Boy-Who-Lived is lying on the ground, and he has a phoenix."

Auror Li passed on the message, then unlocked and activated the Vanishing cabinet - however Director Bones was going to handle this situation, there was no way that she wouldn't start by flooding Azkaban with Aurors. Sure enough, Amelia Bones immediately strode out of the Cabinet with the first part of a substantial fighting force - trio after trio followed on her heels, rapidly filling the command room.

"A1, B1, C1 trios, I want a double sweep of the spirals. Go down fast, come back up as slowly as you need to. Stay in contact with each other and with Auror Li, and report anything suspicious. A2, B2, C2 trios - secure the top of each spiral. Broomstick trios 1, 2 and 3, aerial surveillance of the whole place. Other trios, stay with me. Li, you're in charge of communications - stay here, stay in contact with everyone, and tell me anything I need to hear. McCusker, you're with Li. All of you, we lost Bellatrix Black last time. This time we could lose all of them - today we're looking at a mass breakout. Go!"

Nine trios scattered, all faces grim and all wands out.

"Li, McCusker - there will be more of my people coming through the Cabinet. They're to stay in the command room as reserve forces. Broomstick trios 4 and 5, with me."

Director Bones had already mounted her broomstick, and now she flew out the window and dived down to the bottom of the Pit, broomstick trios 4 and 5 catching up there a moment later and turning outwards to cover the entire area for potential threats.

"Albus. Bahry. What's going on?"

A moment of silence, and then Albus spoke. "When I arrived, I could see nothing except an impossibly bright Patronus charm. When it vanished a few seconds later, Mr Potter was on the ground, and I could see no Dementors. It appears that I was correct to take him seriously in his threat to destroy Azkaban, although I was still unable to prevent him from actually carrying out that threat. Beyond that I know nothing, I'm afraid."

Amelia Bones glanced at the crumpled cloaks, dozens of them, scattered around on the dead soil, and decided to assume for now that the Dementors really had been destroyed - impossible, of course, but seemingly true nonetheless. She turned to the small boy lying unconscious on the ground, his face covered by the phoenix's wings.

"The usual charms revealed no damage beyond normal exhaustion," Albus added.

She turned to him. "Is it safe to wake him now, then?"

"I believe so, yes."

"Innervate."

Harry opened his eyes, and the phoenix moved its wings away from his face. He glanced up at the three adults watching him, craned his neck to look around at the bare earth with its crumpled cloaks, and then smiled. "I did it, didn't I? The only Dementor left in Magical Britain is the one in the Hall of the Wizengamot."

Albus was uncertain and Bahry frankly confused, so it was Amelia who spoke. "Mr Potter, do you confirm that you have destroyed Azkaban's Dementors?"

"Yes, that is correct."

"Was it your intention, or is it now your intention, to instigate a mass breakout from Azkaban?"

Harry paused, then shook his head slightly as he sat up.

"No. My primary goal, as stated before you and the entire Wizengamot, was to prevent Hermione Granger from being exposed to the Dementors of Azkaban. My secondary goal was to end the ongoing torture of prisoners by said Dementors. Actually freeing the prisoners right now would be highly irresponsible, although I would like to see all current sentences reconsidered in light of time already served under ceaseless torture. I trust that the decision to send a child to Azkaban has opened your mind to the possibility that some sentences meted out by our justice system might not be entirely just."

Amelia stared into the boy's face, searching for deceit but finding none. She turned to Dumbledore. "Do you believe him, Albus?"

"Yes. He may play games with words at times, but I have never yet known him to tell a direct lie. That is why I took his threat seriously, and I imagine it is why he has answered you so precisely and unambiguously."

Out of the corner of her eye, Amelia saw Harry nod slightly.

She pulled the mirror from her belt. "Li, what news?"

"Sweep teams are almost at the bottom, broomstick trios are flying circuits, and everyone else is in position. No trouble anywhere, nothing out of the ordinary except that we're in Azkaban without Patronuses and we're all fine."

"Tell the sweep teams they can relax a bit on their way back up, and call the broomstick trios in. The Dementors are gone and Harry Potter is claiming responsibility, but he insists he isn't trying to let the prisoners out. It seems we don't face a mass breakout today. Oh, and tell the Ministry that we don't need any more reinforcements."

"Will do, Director."

She turned back to Harry as he finished standing up, red-yellow bird settled serenely on his shoulder. "Do you have any idea what laws you've just broken?"

He stared at her. "Dementors are the foulest creatures known to me. They should not exist. I understand that the arrangement at Azkaban made political sense given that Dementors existed and couldn't be destroyed, although I strongly disapprove of that arrangement. I do not understand, Director Bones, how any decent human being could sincerely lament the destruction of Dementors, the healing of these wounds in the world."

"I agree with you, Mr Potter. The laws do exist, however, and you would be wise to consider them. As you are of a noble House, the matter will be brought before the Wizengamot. And as you have seen, the Wizengamot as a whole is no ally to you."

"With all due respect, Director Bones, I think I am far safer than that. The Boy-Who-Lived, symbol and champion of the Light, has just destroyed a large number of Dementors, symbols of Darkness. Not even Lucius Malfoy and his half-tame Wizengamot can touch me for that."

She watched his face for a moment longer, and then visibly relaxed. "Thank you, Mr Potter. You are of course correct on all points, and I now trust that you are telling the truth about your intentions. I apologise for interrogating you like this in your weakened state, but I had to be sure that there would be no breakout attempt."

Harry smiled faintly but said nothing, turning instead to the flaming bird on his shoulder. "Are you my phoenix?"

"Caw!"

"What should I call you?"

A pause, a quizzical are-you-stupid look from that glorious creature, and Harry blushed.

"OK, stupid question, but I still need to call you something. I'll call you Bentham if you don't mind, for another prison reformer."

The bird nodded slightly.

"Done, then. Hello Bentham, and thank you. Thank you so much."

Dumbledore raised an eyebrow at this, but forbore to comment. On his shoulder, Fawkes nodded companionably to Bentham.

Chapter 2: A Worried Wizengamot

They arrived together in the Most Ancient Hall of the Wizengamot - two phoenixes, two powerful adults, and the one unfathomable child. Chief Warlock Albus Dumbledore strode to his podium, Fawkes still on his shoulder. Amelia Bones, Director of the Department of Magical Law Enforcement, strode to her accustomed seat. And Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres, with the phoenix Bentham blazing on his shoulder, walked peacefully back to his seat beside Minerva McGonagall. For these few seconds, the Hall at large was silent in shock.

Dumbledore tapped the podium with the rod of the Hall. "The ninetieth session of the two-hundred-and-eighth Wizengamot is resumed. Now, we were discussing the debt owed by Hermione Granger to House Malfoy. I was refusing to allow Harry Potter to go into Lucius Malfoy's debt, and Mr Potter was threatening to destroy Azkaban if this chamber voted to send Miss Granger there. I repeat that I will not allow Harry Potter to go into Lucius Malfoy's debt. Mr Potter?"

Harry stood calmly, the peace of the phoenix washing through him as he faced the confused-looking instrument of death across the chamber from him. "Lord Malfoy, I say once more that I have no desire to be your enemy. I also have no desire to consider you my enemy. Let the debts pay for one another, but let no money change hands between us except the forty Galleons which I owe to your son. Let there be friendship once more between House Potter and House Malfoy."

"You tried to turn my son against me. Your friend tried to kill him. Do you deny it, boy?"

"I do, and I do. Had I intended to turn Draco against you, I would never have told him what I did about your love for him. And the very idea that Hermione Granger would try to kill him, or anyone else for that matter, is absurd. As I said before, we are all caught in a plot which was intended to take your son's life. You're smarter than that, Lord Malfoy."

Lucius Malfoy stared at the boy opposite him. Potter no longer seemed cold or angry, and he had somehow summoned a phoenix. Certain guesses at the boy's true identity no longer made sense, but that raised questions - if the boy wasn't Lucius' old master, then where did this power come from? Just who was this boy, and what did he want? Harry had disappeared for some minutes and then come back, with no explanation given - Lucius suspected that the world had changed in those few minutes, though he wasn't quite sure how. Had Potter really destroyed Azkaban? That seemed frighteningly possible, and in that case the next great power had arrived. Dumbledore was involved, of course, but the way they stood and the way they spoke told Lucius quite plainly that Harry was now in charge. That meddling old fool Dumbledore, the man who for many years had been trying to take over the world, was suddenly deferring to Harry Potter. This felt like the sort of moment that might make or break a life, the sort of moment that a Malfoy couldn't afford to handle badly. The boy might be bluffing, it might all be a trick, but Lucius' finely-honed instincts told him otherwise. The balance had shifted, and House Malfoy must once more shift accordingly. He considered challenging the boy for information, but decided that such a challenge would probably damage his prospects as second-in-command of the new order. And so, after a long pause, Lucius smiled at the Boy-Who-Lived.

"Very well, Mr Potter. The debt owed to House Malfoy by Hermione Granger is now paid in full, by the debt owed by House Malfoy to House Potter. No money need change hands. Let there be friendship between House Malfoy and House Potter. And as a token of that friendship, please consider that debt of 40 Galleons to be settled."

"Thank you, Lord Malfoy." Harry bowed solemnly to Lucius Malfoy, who returned the gesture.

A quiet yet compelling click, and then Dumbledore spoke. "It is done. And now, Mr Potter, please tell this chamber what you have just done."

Knowing his power in this moment, Harry paused fully half a minute to examine the Wizengamot. Throughout this time he stood calm and confident, his face perfectly neutral. The government of Magical Britain, those august representatives of the noble and most ancient Wizengamot, sat in uncomfortable silence. No one tried to interrupt him as he memorised faces and considered what to say. When he spoke, his voice held an unmistakeable note of command.

"Lords and Ladies of the Wizengamot, today you sentenced a twelve-year-old girl to be tortured to death by the Ministry's Dementors in Azkaban. That she was most likely innocent is almost irrelevant here - you voted to send a twelve-year-old girl to Azkaban, and that shame should follow you to the grave. I have made my peace with Lord Malfoy; I bear him no further ill-will. The same cannot be said of the others among you who voted to send my friend to Azkaban."

Harry paused, taking in the state of the Wizengamot. They seemed nervous, perhaps even terrified, but not yet entirely cowed - some among the plum-coloured robes seemed unconvinced, though none so confident as to risk actually challenging him in any way. He continued.

"You have seen the wisdom and prudence of Lord Malfoy. Who among you will follow his example, and make peace with me voluntarily?"

Harry paused once more. No one would speak against him, but no one dared speak first to save themselves either. The bystander effect, of course, and he knew a solution. He could see certain family resemblances, and he was slowly matching names with faces.

"Lady Greengrass, some time ago I offered Daphne my protection. She declined, as it happened, but fortunately her friend Tracey Davis accepted my offer; you've heard that story, I trust. Despite this, you voted to send your daughter's friend, my friend Hermione Granger, to Azkaban. In this time of grace, here in the Most Ancient Hall of the Wizengamot, would you like to apologise?"

Many eyebrows shot up at this, but Lady Greengrass was no fool. And she was, in any case, rather ashamed of her vote - she was not enjoying the intrusion of personal affections into her political life.

"I apologise, Miss Granger, for voting to send you to Azkaban. Please forgive me, and let peace and friendship exist once more between House Granger and House Greengrass."

Hermione's mouth had been opening and shutting silently through all this, but now she managed to speak with surprising composure. "I, I accept your apology, Lady Greengrass. Friends."

Lady Greengrass now bowed her head towards Harry. "Please forgive me, Lord Potter."

Many more eyebrows were raised at this, but Harry was completely composed as he inclined his head towards her. "I forgive you, Lady Greengrass. Let there be friendship between our Houses."

It was a close-run thing, Harry knew, but this was enough - one by one, a large majority of those who had voted against Hermione now apologised both to her and to Harry. And, following the lead of Lady Greengrass, every single one of them addressed him as "Lord Potter".

When it became clear that the few holdouts weren't going to give in immediately, Harry turned to Dumbledore. "Chief Warlock, everyone is calling me 'Lord Potter'. I know that House Potter is a Noble House, and that I am its last scion. What exactly are the restrictions on when I can officially be Lord Potter?"

Dumbledore looked surprised, but only slightly so. "As the last scion, you will acquire your title as soon as you come of age. Normally that would occur when you turn seventeen, but exceptions are possible. A vote in this chamber, for example, could declare you legally adult today. Shall I call the vote?"

Harry nodded. "Thank you, Chief Warlock, yes."

"By show of hands, to recognise Harry Potter as legally adult, and legally the Lord Potter."

Lucius Malfoy's hand was in the air immediately, as were all hands over on what Harry had thought of as Dumbledore's side of the room. The people who had apologised weren't far behind, and by then the vote was clear.

Dumbledore spoke once more. "Lord Potter, before the law of Magical Britain you are now an adult. You now have full control of your vault at Gringott's, and a seat in this chamber. Should you have further questions, please feel free to ask me at any time. And now, Lord Potter, would you please tell your story?"

Harry smiled. "Thank you, Chief Warlock."

He turned to the Wizengamot at large, speaking especially to Lucius Malfoy.

"When you last saw me, I was disappearing from this very spot. As you have all no doubt guessed, from here I was transported instantly to Azkaban - to the central pit, in fact. There I used my Patronus to destroy every Dementor in Azkaban."

Even though they had in theory been expecting this, quite a few people gasped. A scar-faced man to Malfoy's right, one of the few holdouts against Harry Potter, actually stood up and yelled, "Arrest him! Those are national property - he's a traitor for destroying them!"

Dumbledore overrode him with a click of that rod. "Lord Jugson, once more you are out of line. Dementors were national possessions only so long as we had no way to destroy them - now that Lord Potter has eliminated them, I think that every sane adult in the country will merely breathe a sigh of relief. In any case, this chamber will certainly not entertain any suggestion that Lord Potter be punished for the tremendous service he has rendered to Magical Britain today. And Lord Jugson, if I may speak plainly? This young man, now recognised as Lord Potter, has succeeded today where Merlin himself tried and failed. As his headmaster I know of yet other magicks which he alone can wield, magicks which even I cannot comprehend. I know of no malice in him, Lord Jugson, but in any case I would suggest that opposing Lord Potter is extremely unwise. The world has changed, Lord Jugson. Truly, the world has changed."

Lord Jugson appeared to be struggling with his temper, but managed to hold his tongue and retake his seat. Harry continued.

"As I was saying, I destroyed every Dementor in Azkaban. As far as I'm aware, that thing 'guarding' Hermione right now is the only Dementor in all of Magical Britain. I haven't yet decided whether to destroy it also; I am open to suggestions on that point. I'm not sure whether anyone actually saw my Patronus, by the way, but Chief Warlock Dumbledore and Director Bones can both confirm that there are now no Dementors in Azkaban."

Every member of the Wizengamot looked either at Albus Dumbledore or at Amelia Bones for confirmation; both of them nodded, and Harry went on.

"That was quite a strain for me - I am only eleven years old, after all - so afterwards I passed out. When I woke up, I saw lots of people but no Dementors. Chief Warlock Dumbledore and Director Bones were both there, along with a large number of aurors. Director Bones asked me some questions and then scaled back the security operation, and then we came back here."

Harry paused, appreciating the confused expressions on the faces around the Hall. There were many questions to be asked of him, but it seemed that no one could think of any in particular right now. He went on.

"In that discussion with Director Bones, I assured her that I was not attempting to break anyone out of Azkaban. However, I do want every single prisoner in that hellhole to have their sentence reviewed. As I said to Director Bones, I trust that this morning's decision has opened your minds to the possibility that some sentences are perhaps not entirely just. Given that time spent in Azkaban is time spent under ceaseless torture, I feel that time already served should count for quite a lot when we reconsider those sentences."

No one moved, no one spoke. The Wizengamot was stunned into silence, so Harry continued.

"I call the vote, then. By show of hands, that the sentences of all current Azkaban inmates be reviewed."

This vote also passed with overwhelming support - these were experienced politicians, all of them, and few were foolish enough now to fight against such an overwhelming tide. The world had shifted, and they all knew it.

Dumbledore now spoke. "Done, then - there will be a review of all current Azkaban sentences. Any further business for the chamber?"

After a brief pause to establish that there was apparently no such business, Dumbledore continued.

"There being no further matters to consider, the ninetieth session of the two-hundred-and-eighth Wizengamot is now concluded."

He tapped his podium three more times with the dark rod, and the session was over.

Chapter 3: A New Adult

As soon as Dumbledore tapped the podium, Harry was racing down the stairs towards Hermione - Bentham on his shoulder sped his passage dramatically, but Harry had no attention to spare for anything except his best friend. She stood up awkwardly as he approached, her face showing blank confusion.

"Harry, what? Just... what?"

Harry took her hands gently. "The world just changed, Hermione. Everything's pretty much OK now and I suddenly have a lot more power, although sooner or later it's all going to go horribly wrong, of course."

"Am I still sworn to you?"

"Technically yes, though I can probably release you if you want me to. I promise it's nothing more than a legal technicality to me, though, and it might be useful - this legal system is practically medieval, and I'm pretty sure a Muggleborn like you has much better legal protections if you're in service to a Noble and Most Ancient House. Do you want me to release you anyway?"

"No, you're probably right. I'll think it over later, and I'll let you know if I change my mind."

Harry nodded, and then they both fell silent. After a few moments, Professor McGonagall spoke. "Miss Granger, are you OK?"

Hermione smiled weakly. "Probably not."

She swayed slightly, and Harry stepped forward to catch her as she fell. She felt surprisingly light in his arms, and he remembered that he had a phoenix on his shoulder. He shifted his grip so that he was cradling her, and then looked up at Professor McGonagall.

"I think she's just exhausted, Professor. Should I take her to Madam Pomfrey?"

McGonagall nodded. "Thank you, Mr Potter. I shan't make this an order, but I would like to see you in my office sometime soon - I think we have some matters to discuss, you and I."

Harry nodded. "I was about to ask you the same thing, Professor. I'd be happy to speak to you as soon as I've handed Hermione over to Madam Pomfrey, if you're free. Would you like a lift back to Hogwarts?"

She paused a moment at that, before laying a hand on Harry's shoulder in assent. A moment later, the four of them flickered away from the Great Hall of the Wizengamot.

They flared back into existence inside the infirmary at Hogwarts, making Madam Pomfrey jump with fright. Before Madam Pomfrey could say anything, though, Harry laid Hermione gently on a nearby bed and turned to the healer. "I think she's just exhausted, but she's had a traumatic morning. I'd greatly appreciate your help and expertise, Madam Pomfrey."

She looked faintly indignant, but her immediate concern for a patient overrode all other considerations. She rapidly cast a series of diagnostic charms on the young witch, before visibly relaxing as she turned back towards Harry, Bentham and Professor McGonagall. "Indeed, nothing more than exhaustion. I'll give her a restorative potion when she wakes up, and then she'll probably be ready to leave. Is there anything else I should know about her traumatic morning?"

Harry shook his head, and then they took their leave of Madam Pomfrey and her infirmary. Neither Harry nor Professor McGonagall spoke on the way to her office, each taking the other's silence as confirmation that this conversation needed to be private. Once they were inside her office, Professor McGonagall closed the door and cast nine separate spells, of which Harry recognised five from Mr Bester and Professor Quirrell.

Minerva sat down behind her desk, and Harry perched on the soft chair in front of it. Bentham ruffled his feathers slightly, but stayed on Harry's shoulder. Harry and Minerva looked at each other for a moment, and then Minerva spoke.

"Harry, you did a great thing today. No, you did great things. You saved Hermione from an unthinkable fate. You seem to have turned the Wizengamot wholly to the side of Light in a matter of minutes. You emancipated yourself, with all that that entails. And, most importantly, you cleansed Azkaban. Thank you, Harry. Thank you. I believe the entire wizarding world owes you a debt of gratitude - I certainly do."

Harry smiled beatifically, the peace of the phoenix strong within him. "Thank you, Professor. Honestly, though, I just did what I had to do. I'd die before I'd let Hermione be eaten by Dementors. Actually I think I nearly did die, but that's another story."

Minerva winced at Harry's brush with death, and her face became more serious. She hesitated a moment, and then spoke again.

"Be careful, Harry - I should be most sorry to lose you, and I fear that you do not fully appreciate the dangers that you face. And with that... A moment, Mr Potter, if you don't mind. I need to think."

She pressed her face into her hands, tendons standing taut in her neck. This child in front of her wasn't entirely a child, she knew, but he was still her responsibility. And yet it was still a child's body that sat so rigid on the chair in front of her, a child's face looking at her. This was a first-year, for heaven's sake. How could she reconcile that with his belief that he was somehow responsible for the entire world? With the Wizengamot's mad ruling that Harry should be an adult already? It was all too much to ask of a boy, and yet he never complained. He grew angry only when she tried to shield him, tried to preserve some hint of childhood for him. Clearly he wanted to be an adult, and wanted to be treated as such. And, given that his wishes were so clear, had he not earned this? Had he not earned the right to be called an adult, if he so chose? It would mean breaking her role, stepping away from the stern-but-fair disciplinarian she always tried to be. It would mean making herself vulnerable. And yet it was, she ultimately decided, the right thing to do. And once she had decided that, her duty was clear. Not easy - never easy - but clear. She raised her head, and deliberately looked Harry Potter full in the face.

"I have decided that I should not be treating you like a normal student, like a child. I've tried so hard to make you fit my idea of what a Hogwarts first-year should be, and I now think that was a mistake. For that, Mr Potter, I am sorry. I still expect you to treat both me and my fellow staff members with respect, mind you, and in public I will still treat you like any other student, but here and now I acknowledge you as an adult. In private you may call me Minerva if you wish, although I'm afraid I must still insist that you address me more formally in public."

Harry nodded, smiling warmly. "Thank you, Minerva. I appreciate it - I really do."

She smiled back, reassured that she had made the right decision.

"And Harry, as a gesture... No, wait. I'm terribly sorry, Mr Potter, but this requires further thought."

Her face returned to her hands, but more calmly this time. She deliberately relaxed her shoulders as she considered the problem before her. She had wondered, off and on, whether she had done right in locking Harry's Time-Turner after that business with the Ministry. She had wondered more after Bellatrix Black's escape, with the implacable determination that he seemed to have acquired then. And now the question of safety loomed large - after what had happened to Draco Malfoy, she couldn't very well insist that Harry would never need his Time-Turner to escape from mortal peril in Hogwarts. She was beginning to appreciate that the future of the world might actually depend on Harry Potter, and to fear for that future if he didn't survive to adulthood. Thinking that way, Ministry restrictions on Time-Turner use suddenly seemed rather less important. There would be trouble if anyone found out, of course, but that was no longer a good enough reason for her to leave one of Harry's major defences crippled. She lifted her head once more.

"Harry, some time ago I locked your Time-Turner in order to prevent you from further misusing it. As a gesture of respect and of friendship, and in recognition of the dangers you now face and the maturity with which you face them, I am willing to remove that restriction. I must warn you, however, that the Ministry does track their use and misuse. You very nearly lost this last time, Harry. If you misuse it again, I will not be able to protect you. You will lose your Time-Turner, and you and I will both be punished. Do you understand?"

Harry's eyebrows had shot up, and there was a distinct element of surprise even in his phoenix-calm voice as he replied. "Thank you, Minerva. Thank you very much. I understand perfectly, and I promise I will be very careful. I realise the personal risk you're taking for my sake, and I am profoundly grateful. I have nothing equivalent to offer in return, but please tell me anytime I can help you with anything."

He handed over his Time-Turner, and she removed the timed locking charm. After a moment's thought, she cast a Charm of Unbreakability on the Time-Turner's protective shell before handing it back. Harry bowed to her, and she spoke once more.

"Harry, you are more powerful now, but you are still vulnerable. The fate of Magical Britain at the very least depends on your actions even now, and it is vitally important that you have good advisors. Your intelligence is beyond question, but you are young, and you do not yet fully understand many of the areas in which you choose to intervene. Miss Granger is sensible and knowledgeable and also extremely clever, and you should certainly listen to her, but there is much that she also does not yet know. I very much fear that you do not yet have adequate counsel available to you, and the importance of such counsel could hardly be plainer. Ordinarily I would encourage you to seek out the Headmaster for advice, but you and I both know that you won't.

"I've known Albus Dumbledore for many long years, Mr Potter. I have worked with him, relaxed with him, fought a war by his side. Without him I would not be alive today. Please understand, my loyalty to Albus runs deep. I would risk my life to save his, in a heartbeat, even now."

She looked away from Harry, taking a few deep breaths before she looked back to him and continued.

"For many years I have disagreed with the Headmaster on some matters, but I have always trusted that he knew best. Since you arrived at Hogwarts, however, I've found myself disagreeing with him both more frequently and more sharply. I could not even bear to be present when Severus punished Miss Granger for doing what was right; I yelled at Albus when I learned what was planned, but he refused to listen. And today, this morning, I watched my old friend fight to let a twelve-year-old girl be sent to Azkaban. I watched you, an eleven-year-old boy, stand against the most powerful wizard in Magical Britain and do what was right. And so, Mr Potter, I understand why you feel you cannot trust Albus Dumbledore. It breaks my heart to say this, but I believe you are right.

"Harry, I believe that you hold the future of Magical Britain in your hands. You proved this morning that you are willing to do what is right, no matter the difficulty. Albus, alas, proved the contrary. "

Minerva McGonagall leaned forward across her desk, face deadly serious. "Harry, from now on I shall place your interests and wishes above Albus'. Permanently. You will tell no one of this offer. Do you understand?"

Even floating in the peace of the phoenix, Harry was shocked by that. His jaw dropped slightly, and he goggled at Minerva McGonagall as he frantically reconsidered his assessment of her. After a few seconds, he concluded that she was in any case trying to help him - he could puzzle over the reasons later.

"Thank you, Minerva. I... Um. Thank you. I don't really know what else to say, but I am so incredibly grateful to you."

He looked down at his feet, his breathing rapid and shallow as he fought to control his emotions. This took some time, but eventually he raised his head again.

"I gratefully accept your offer, and I apologise for misjudging you in the past."

"Apology accepted. Now, Harry, you have placed yourself in significant danger, and the attack on Draco Malfoy shows that there are other dangers to consider also. You do still have powerful enemies in the Wizengamot, particularly in the person of Lord Jugson, and I do not believe that you are safe in Hogwarts as things currently stand. Do you have any immediate plans to make yourself safer?"

Minerva set parchment on the desk before her and took up a quill, and Harry leaned forward slightly. "That's actually why I wanted to see you. I completely agree that Hogwarts isn't safe, and I want to make it safe - for me and my friends, of course, but also for everyone. I'd very much appreciate your advice and your help with that - I think it's time for Hogwarts to take security seriously.

"I already have a Time-Turner, and you've very kindly removed the prior restrictions on its use - thanks again for that - but I want Time-Turners to give to my friends as well. Er... By 'my friends' I mean Hermione, Neville, and Draco. Rest assured that I'll talk to each of them first, particularly Draco, before giving out such dangerous items - I won't hand anything over unless I'm satisfied that it's safe to do so. That being said, I want them as well-equipped as we can manage. I already have an invisibility cloak, which incidentally is one of the Deathly Hallows, but I want my friends to have the best cloaks that money can buy."

Minerva broke in at this point, her voice shaking with the shock of it. "Your cloak is the Cloak of Invisibility?"

Harry nodded calmly, lips twitching only slightly. "I believe so, yes. That's what Dumbledore said when he gave it to me, anyway, although technically that was all anonymous and he wrote it in a note. Anyway, apparently it was my dad's, and he lent it to Dumbledore just before he died."

Minerva was still staring at Harry, trying to understand what it meant that he was giving her this information. As if reading that in her face, he changed tack slightly.

"The reason I'm telling you this is that you've just given me a lot of trust, and I think you deserve the same in return. Plus I really need your help, and it'd be pretty stupid for me not to give you all the information I can before I ask you for advice."

He paused, closing his eyes for a moment as he collected his thoughts.

"That first day in Diagon Alley, I told you that I'd never been able to trust my parents to be reasonable. But it's more than that, Professor - I've never known an adult that I could trust completely, even now. Dumbledore is brilliant and powerful, and I think he's spent his whole life trying to do what's right, but I can't trust his judgement, and I can't trust him not to get in my way when we disagree. Quirrell thinks clearly, more clearly than I do even at my best, but I can't trust him to be good. You're the only other adult that I know well, and until now I thought you were trapped in the role you were playing. So you see, I haven't had an adult I could trust. I think you've just become an adult that I can trust, and I really really want you to know how much that means to me. There are still some things that are genuinely too dangerous for me to tell you right now - I'm really sorry about that - but I promise you that I will be totally open and honest with you about everything that I can without breaking oaths."

Minerva stared intently at this strange serious adult in the body of a child, beginning to realise that even now she had underestimated both him and the situation. She nodded slowly, and he continued.

"Actually, I may even decide that it's worth breaking an oath in order to give you information. I'll have to think about that, though, so for now I'll stick to safer topics. Anyway, feel free to ask me any questions at all in private - the worst that can happen is that I say I can't answer."

She nodded, and he went on.

"So, I'd covered Time-Turners and invisibility cloaks. I also want each of us to have at least one spare wand, properly matched to us like our current wands are - money is no object, and wands are just too important to risk being without. I also want each of us to have a pouch like the one I have. I want each of us to have a three-person broomstick to put in that pouch, and a toe-ring portkey in case we're kidnapped and taken outside Hogwarts' wards. Oh, and I want each of us to have a reliable and effective way to call for help. Say a panic button that alerts the rest of us, including you, Professor, and gives location and hopefully some sort of two-way communications. That's about it for us specifically - what do you think?"

Minerva looked at Harry a moment longer, then glanced down at her parchment.

"I very much doubt that I can obtain further Time-Turners, I'm afraid - they are highly restricted, and I am taking a substantial risk even unlocking yours for you. We can ask Filius about invisibility cloaks - he will know either where to buy them or how to make them, and I trust him. I do not, however, trust Draco Malfoy - we shall have to discuss that particular question with Filius, since we need his help in that matter anyway. Spare wands are an excellent idea, given that you possess great wealth and face tremendous danger - if I am to fight alongside you, perhaps I should even buy a spare wand myself. Pouches and broomsticks are a good idea also, and present no great difficulty. Portkeys may be a little more difficult, but I think we can manage - again, I strongly recommend that we ask Filius for help. We will certainly want his help for this 'panic button' that you suggest - I could manage a basic cry for help and perhaps something for location, but that would be my limit."

Harry nodded. "Thank you. We can talk more later, just you and I, but should we bring Professor Flitwick into this conversation now? I'm not ready to trust him the way I'm trusting you, but I do trust him to help me make this school safer."

Minerva nodded. After a wave of her wand and a pinch of Floo powder, she said "Ravenclaw Head of House office" and stuck her head into the green flames dancing merrily in the hearth. Harry couldn't hear what she said, but a moment later she withdrew her head and stood up again. Another moment, and Filius Flitwick spun out of the flames. His wand dangled loosely from his fingertips, but his eyes were intent as he took in the room in a single graceful spin. Suddenly the tiny man didn't seem comical at all to Harry.

Flitwick spoke first, glancing at the unknown phoenix on Harry's shoulder. "What happened at the trial?"

Harry briefly recounted the events of the morning.

After a pause to absorb the information, Flitwick addressed Harry soberly.

"Very well. A remarkable achievement, Mr Potter - another time, I shall ask you how you achieved that which Merlin himself could not. For now, Minerva said you required my help with some security precautions?"

Harry nodded, and then relayed to Filius the security precautions that he and Minerva had been discussing, including Minerva's comments. Filius looked somewhat impressed.

"Excellent thinking. Minerva is correct on all counts, though I cannot guarantee invisibility cloaks - they are difficult to make, and even more difficult to purchase. You and I must talk at length to design those panic buttons, but they should be easy enough for me to make once I know exactly what you want."

Harry inclined his head. "Thank you, Filius."

Filius fixed Harry with a penetrating look.

"Before any of this, however, you will explain to me why I should desire that a group of first-year students have invisibility cloaks. Especially, Mr Potter, a group containing Draco Malfoy."

Harry met Filius' eyes unflinchingly.

"Draco especially needs this protection, Professor. He nearly died, and he's an obvious target for future attacks. Not only would his loss hurt me, but it would have dramatic effects on Lord Malfoy - we saw that this morning. I acknowledge that he could misuse an invisibility cloak, but that risk is insignificant compared to the risk that he will actually die next time."

"Very well, Harry. Just be aware that you bear partial responsibility if Mr Malfoy does indeed abuse his cloak. Or Hermione or Neville, for that matter."

"Duly acknowledged, Professor, and thank you."

Filius now looked intently into Harry's eyes.

"You mentioned protecting other students, Harry, beyond just you and your friends. What did you have in mind?"

In the corner of his eye, Harry noticed Minerva leaning forward with her elbows on her desk. Filius had absently and wordlessly conjured a chair some time ago, and Harry himself was perched once more on Minerva's usual visitor chair. He grinned somewhat manically.

"I've got a whole new security system planned, which should actually make this crazy castle safe for the children who have to live in it. And I mean safe against anything, from ordinary bullying all the way up to an actual army attacking from inside the castle."

"Ambitious. How would you achieve this?"

"Well, it basically boils down to a stronghold and the means to reach it. For a stronghold I suggest the infirmary, since healing will be crucial in most emergency scenarios anyway. I say we put serious security on it - everything we can think of that won't interfere with its day-to-day operations, plus an extra set of protections that we can activate if we no longer care about its day-to-day operations. We should add a special secure room, accessible only via the infirmary, and able to house basically the entire population of the castle if necessary. Oh, and that room should be accessible to Hogwarts house elves - we'll need food in any sustained emergency, and I believe that the kitchens are well-protected.

"So that's the stronghold, anyway. Next we need a ward on the castle which automatically teleports injured people to the infirmary - I want this to work both by the sudden-damage measure that's currently used for the Headmaster's alarms, and by the absolute-health test that Quirrell apparently put on Draco Malfoy. It might be a good idea to give people an option to refuse the teleport, but only if they consciously choose to stay - by default, anyone who really needs medical attention should get it. Er... It occurs to me that this needs to be specific to known residents of Hogwarts - we don't want enemies to be able to get into our stronghold just by stubbing a toe or something. Oh, and there also needs to be a way for students to activate this teleport manually to get themselves out of danger. That needs to be easy for even a new first-year to manage, so the power has to come from the wards.

"That's the main security system I want, anyway. The only other thing is bullying, and I'd like a general policy that any and all bullying that's reported from now on will be verified by either Veritaserum or a Pensieve - using the victim's memories in either case, so the bully can't refuse to cooperate. I don't think this is quite as important now as it would have been before Hermione and her friends and then that amazing ritual, but I think it's still worth doing if we can."

Minerva spoke up.

"Harry, we can't force victims of bullying to take Veritaserum. I won't allow it."

"Good point, Professor - that will have to be strictly optional."

Minerva nodded, mollified, and she and Harry both turned to Filius.

Filius gazed at Harry for a few seconds before speaking.

"Very impressive, Harry - you really have thought this through. I think your plan is excellent, but we will most certainly require Albus Dumbledore's help. Have you considered how we might persuade him?"

"Not really, to be honest - I guessed that we might need his help, but I just hoped I'd be able to talk him into it. I haven't really planned beyond that. The only reason I've been able to give you such complete plans is because I was thinking about it between the arrest and the trial. I had no idea what was going to happen this morning, and I haven't had time to do much thinking with that information in mind. At this point I'm just hoping I can talk him into it, preferably now before the shock wears off."

Minerva, sitting at her desk with several sheets of notes, interjected at this point.

"Shall we go and see Albus now, then?"

Harry and Filius nodded, and the three of them headed for the door.

Chapter 6: Rethink

As the other students filed quietly out of the classroom, mostly seeming to be lost in thought, Harry and the phoenixes stayed behind with Professor McGonagall. She gave him a questioning look, but he flicked his eyes briefly to the departing students and said nothing. She nodded faintly and waited.

When the last of the other students had left the room and gone out of sight down the corridor, Harry walked over and closed the door. As he walked back toward Minerva, she cast a few privacy charms - she did so almost absently, Harry noted.

"Thanks for letting me speak to the class - I think that few minutes might really make a difference. Sorry if it ends up getting you into trouble with the Headmaster."

Minerva shrugged slightly. "I've made my choice, Mr Potter. All I ask is that you don't make me regret it."

Harry nodded seriously. "Of course. Cutting class to go see Hermione now wouldn't count as that, would it?"

Minerva shook her head. "Not at all, young man, not at all. By all means go and see your friend - I rather suspect she'll need you."

Harry turned and almost ran towards the door, as Minerva hastily canceled her wards to allow him out. She watched him go, a faint smile upon her ancient face.

Once outside the door, Harry paused for a moment before flickering and disappearing. A moment later he stood at the doors of the infirmary, feeling faintly stupid for not having planned to use phoenix travel in the first place.

Madam Pomfrey strode over as Harry entered.

"Shouldn't you be in class, young man?"

Harry's Gryffindor side favoured direct honesty, confident that Madam Pomfrey would be sympathetic. Slytherin outright laughed at this, and it was left to Ravenclaw to point out to Gryffindor that Madam Pomfrey was perhaps not quite so sympathetic and adaptable as all that. After a moment's reflection, even Gryffindor had to concede the point.

"I just wanted to see my best friend, Madam Pomfrey. She's been hurt very badly in the last day or two, and I really want to be here for her when she wakes up. Professor McGonagall said it was OK."

Madam Pomfrey subsided slightly. "Very well. Just don't let her get excited - she needs her rest."

"I'll do what I can."

He walked quickly to the bed where Hermione lay, seeming to relax slightly as he drew near to her. He took a seat next to her bed, and gazed absently at her face.

He suddenly understood Lucius Malfoy's promise about Draco's wellbeing - Harry himself now knew that he felt much the same way about Hermione. However he might justify it in utilitarian terms, that was nothing more than post-hoc rationalisation - the truth was that he would protect her with his life because in his world her loss was unthinkable. He had nearly lost her, had been incredibly lucky not to lose her - he had risked his life in Azkaban and achieved an insanely improbable victory in order to save her. And the thing about improbable victories was that you couldn't make a habit of them, because in the real world you'd usually just lose. He needed to shift the odds a long way in his and her favour, and other considerations suddenly seemed a lot less important.

As he emerged from this contemplation, he became aware of Professor Flitwick standing quietly on the other side of the bed. The tiny man inclined his head to Harry.

"I came straight here from Albus' office, and have been with her ever since. She hasn't stirred."

"Thank you, Professor. I'd have been here myself, but I needed to be in Transfiguration."

Flitwick paused at that, and looked thoughtfully at Harry.

"I hadn't wondered at your absence until now, but I see that there's more to this. Why exactly did you need to be in Transfiguration?"

"Well, for a start I didn't want to let Professor McGonagall down. But you're right, there is more - mostly that I really needed the chance to talk to my fellow students about what just happened, and the sooner the better. Pre-empting rumours is helpful, of course, but the main thing is that I'm possibly going to be moving against the Headmaster quite soon - I need support for that."

Filius looked sharply at Harry. "What exactly do you mean by moving against the Headmaster, may I ask? I never agreed to support a revolution."

"Oh no, nothing like that! Um... Look, I'll try to be precise here. I don't intend to displace Albus Dumbledore from his current position as Headmaster. I just want to apply enough pressure to make him actually listen to our concerns about security in Hogwarts."

Filius sighed. "I have known Albus Dumbledore for a very long time, Harry. I now believe that it was a mistake for us to meet him head-on in his office earlier today, and I assure you that your current plans will merely confirm him in his current position. You can try to reassure him that you yourself are not about to destroy the world - that might help. You can try to remove him as Headmaster - that would work if you managed it, though there would be consequences for such an action. What you cannot do, I'm afraid, is to openly force the greatest wizard of our time to follow a course of action which he has decided is unwise. Put simply, Mr Potter, you cannot win a dominance contest against Albus Dumbledore. I advise you not to try, and I warn you that I will not support you in any such challenge."

Harry frowned. "I see your point - I'll have to think about that. Would you recommend any particular course of action, Professor?"

Filius shrugged. "Go to see him, alone, and negotiate. Be ready to make concessions. I will help you with anything to make the castle safer, but I'm afraid I can't change the Headmaster's mind."

"Thank you. I'll do that, and I'll try very very hard not to get into a dominance contest."

Filius nodded. "Yes, do that. I wish you luck. And now, I believe that Miss Granger would prefer to see you rather than me when she wakes - if Madam Pomfrey asks, you have my permission to be here. If you need me, touch your wand to this and I'll return immediately."

He tossed Harry a Sickle, then left quietly.

Some time later, Hermione finally stirred. Her eyes fell on Harry, and she smiled tentatively and held out her hand. He took it and returned her smile. They sat in silence for a time, before Harry finally broke the silence.

"So how do you feel?"

"Surprisingly good, actually. I'm completely exhausted, of course, but nothing actually hurts."

"That's good."

"I probably should still feel guilty about Draco, even if you're right about what actually happened, but somehow I just can't make myself care."

"Well that's good, because you shouldn't be feeling bad about that anyway. I mean honestly, you'd be demanding way too much of yourself if you really felt bad just because you didn't immediately face the music when you believed that you'd done something really big and scary. You're a human being, Hermione, and probably the most moral person I've ever met - you feel OK because no one's seriously hurt and you didn't actually do anything very terrible. You failed in one small and totally understandable way, and you can learn from that, but in the end everyone's OK. Seem fair?"

She nodded. "OK, fair enough. So what now? Where do we go from here?"

"Well, the other students are probably just going to forget about this - to most of them you're probably still guilty, but what I did is so big and strange that it'll bury that. Beyond that, I really want you protected from Legilimency so that I can tell you my secrets. I'm finished with keeping things from you, at least where I have a choice."

Her eyebrows shot up. "Um... Wow. Thanks? I think? Um... Well, I've read about Occlumency and I don't think that I could do it - I'm way too young, and I really don't think my mind is… is twisty enough to do that kind of pretending. I don't know if there's another way. I'll research that, if you like."

He nodded, and she went on. "But Harry, why do you suddenly want to tell me your secrets? And what secrets have you been keeping from me, anyway?"

Harry stood up and pulled the privacy curtain around Hermione's bed, casting the sound-blurring charm as he did so. He sat now on Hermione's bed rather than on the chair, leaning in close and speaking softly.

"Hermione, I know a lot of secrets. Some of the things I know could even get people killed - believe me, I have good reason to guard my secrets. That's why I did learn Occlumency - there are people in this school who read students' minds, and these are not people that I trust with all my secrets."

Harry paused for a moment, and looked directly into Hermione's eyes. "As for why I suddenly want to tell you... Hermione, I nearly lost you today, and it scared me. Terrified me. It made me think about the gap you'd leave in my life, and what you mean to me. And then I realised that, if I value you this much, I really should tell you a whole lot more and work with you much more as an equal. And no, I am not planning to make Draco a similar offer. I'll admit that I like him and I do genuinely want to be friends with him as well as redeeming him, but there's no way I could trust him the way I trust you."

Hermione nodded slowly. "So you're promising to tell me all of your secrets, or at least most of them, as soon as you're sure no one can steal them out of my head?"

"Pretty much, yeah. You'll need to trust me, though - there are things you won't like, things that will make you think differently about me. Things that would make you sure that I actually had been sucked into the darkness like you said I was, except that I've got two phoenixes on my shoulders right now and you have some idea what that means. Um… So, are you willing to deal with that?"

She nodded. "Yes, of course, though I might be angry at first. But really, you're asking Ravenclaw me whether or not I want knowledge. Think about that."

"True - that was a bit silly of me. Hmm… Professor Flitwick was here before you woke up, and he left me a coin to call him with if I needed him. Do you mind if I call him back and ask him about ways to protect you from Legilimency?"

Hermione waved a hand impatiently. "Yes, of course - good idea."

Harry tapped the Sickle with his wand, and then canceled the sound-blurring charm and swept away the curtain around Hermione's bed. A few moments later, a slightly out-of-breath Filius Flitwick entered the infirmary and walked briskly over to Harry and Hermione.

"How are you feeling now, Miss Granger?"

"Fine, thank you Professor, and I apologise for making you rush back here."

He waved a hand dismissively, and Hermione continued.

"Professor, other than Occlumency, do you know of any effective defence against Legilimency?"

Flitwick looked surprised for a moment, but then realised. "Oh of course, that would have prevented this whole mess in the first place. Hmm…"

He sat down absently, face intent, and sat silently for several minutes (Harry noted approvingly that he spent actual whole minutes, by the clock, thinking about the problem). Eventually Flitwick looked up, face serious.

"I have a solution, Miss Granger, but there is a drawback. The best plan I can think of at present will simply block your sight any time you are subject to Legilimency. This will leave you somewhat helpless against other attacks, although the darkness will lift as soon as you turn away. Either way, it should at the very least ensure that your secrets cannot be stolen without your noticing. We can take other precautions to guard your general safety, of course."

Hermione and Harry both looked extremely curious at that, but Hermione was fractionally quicker to speak. "How does it work?"

"In short, Legilimency requires eye contact. I will cast a ward on you, anchored in your eyeballs, which will temporarily conjure an opaque barrier over each of your pupils if Legilimency is detected. This is new and untried, but I expect that from a Legilimens' point of view it will look and feel like a new type of Occlumency barrier. Do you wish to try it, Miss Granger?"

She nodded nervously. He aimed his wand at each of her eyes in turn, and muttered a lengthy incantation which neither Hermione nor Harry could even begin to parse. Hermione's pupils glowed white for a moment, and she flinched but said nothing.

Flitwick lowered his wand. "I'm not a particularly good Legilimens myself, never having practiced the art, but my skills should suffice for testing. May I, Miss Granger?"

She nodded, and stared bravely into his eyes. A moment later, both Hermione and Professor Flitwick recoiled.

"My word!" said Professor Flitwick. "I'm not quite sure why, but that actually hurt! I'd call that a rousing success, at least from my perspective - anyone who tries to invade your mind in future will be thrown out with a sharp slap. Did that test hurt you at all, Hermione?"

Hermione shook her head. "I was just surprised, that's all. Everything went black, very suddenly. It only lasted a split-second, though - it's just a shock when it happens."

"That's even better," Harry said. "You don't even need to turn away to clear your eyes, so you'll be much safer than we thought. Professor Flitwick, thank you very much."

Hermione hastened to add her own thanks, profoundly grateful to be safe inside her own head.

The tiny man bowed gracefully, a smile visible in his puffy white beard, before taking his leave.

Chapter 8: Questions

Only a few minutes after Harry and Hermione had returned to the infirmary, the curtain was pulled back and Dumbledore stepped in. The Headmaster smiled genially at Hermione.

"How are you feeling, Miss Granger?"

"Much better," she said. "Can I leave the infirmary now?"

Dumbledore looked thoughtful for a moment, then nodded.

"Very well, unless Madam Pomfrey has a specific reason to keep you here. However, you must return here immediately if you feel faint or ill."

Hermione readily agreed to that, of course.

"Headmaster," Harry said after a moment, "I think I made a mistake earlier today, in taking such a confrontational approach to you. I apologise for that – if you can spare the time, would you be willing to meet with Hermione and me some time today for a much friendlier chat?"

Dumbledore gave him a searching look, but then nodded.

"Certainly, Harry, certainly. If you would both like to follow me, we can go to my office right now."

Harry nodded. Fawkes flickered across to Dumbledore's shoulder, and the old man positively beamed. A moment later he and Fawkes vanished. Hermione stood up and reached out to take Harry's hand, but stopped abruptly and strode instead to Madam Pomfrey's office.

"Madam Pomfrey, may I go now? I'm perfectly fine, and Professor Dumbledore wants to see me in his office now."

Madam Pomfrey glared at the girl before her, but could see nothing obviously wrong with her.

"Very well, but you're to come straight back here if you feel faint."

"Yes, Madam Pomfrey."

Harry took her hand, and Bentham flamed the two of them directly into the Headmaster's office.

"Headmaster, you say that you aren't willing to upgrade the wards until you're satisfied that I'm not a threat to the Wizarding world. What can I do to reassure you on that point?"

Dumbledore looked up at the boy and sighed.

"I'm afraid it's not so simple as that, Harry. I doubt neither your intentions nor your sincerity in this moment, so no mere words from you can reassure me. You are dangerous, young man, and all the more so as you cannot see it."

"Wait," said Hermione. "Doesn't that mean that Harry could reassure you by acknowledging how dangerous he is?"

Dumbledore stared at her for a moment, then inclined his head to her.

"That would certainly be a start."

Harry stepped forward.

"OK, Professor. I want to change the world, and I think I can. That has to mean I also have the power to break it. So, we agree on that. I think the difference is that I'm sure I wouldn't do that, but you think I might go Dark. Or maybe that I already am Dark, I'm not sure. I definitely think quite differently to you, so I can see where you're coming from."

Dumbledore nodded, and Harry went on.

"I can't really explain how my worldview stops me from going Dark, because you can't understand it well enough for that. Um... I probably should have planned this a bit better. Give me a moment..."

Long seconds later, Harry suddenly jumped.

"Of course! Headmaster, I have the perfect assurance for you: Hermione! I can promise you right now that I won't ever do anything that she tells me not to do. And... Um, this bit itself is a pretty big secret..."

"I will keep your confidences, Mr Potter. Carry on."

"Well, Hermione knows my secrets now. She's the only person who does, and that's how it's going to stay. But if you trust her to be good, then you can trust me to be good. Or at least not to do anything seriously bad."

Dumbledore looked genuinely shocked.

"Harry, I know you to possess secrets which could do a great deal of damage if they were to be exposed. While I would not question Miss Granger's integrity, have you not considered the possibility that someone might violate her mental privacy? You may have learned Occlumency, but to my knowledge she has not."

Harry closed his eyes for a few moments as he consciously calmed himself down - it was a reasonable point, the headmaster couldn't reasonably have anticipated Flitwick's solution, and getting angry would be neither reasonable nor helpful.

"Hermione's mind is protected by different defences, Headmaster. You're right - I didn't dare tell her my secrets until I was sure she couldn't simply have them plucked out of her head."

Dumbledore frankly stared at him. "You have proved me wrong before, young man, but once more I find myself caught in sheer disbelief. Can you tell me the nature of this protection?"

Hermione cut in. "It's a charm that Professor Flitwick cast - I think he might have invented it on the spot, or at least modified an existing spell when I asked him. It's probably simpler to demonstrate than to explain - would you like to try to read my mind, Headmaster, in order to see for yourself what happens? He did describe the experience as 'a sharp slap', though."

Dumbledore looked thoughtfully at Hermione, then nodded slightly. A moment later, he flinched. His jaw dropped, and for long seconds he frankly stared. Finally he nodded his head slowly. "Very well - your mind certainly is well-protected, Miss Granger. And Harry, I take your point - whilever you are bound by Miss Granger's morality, you are indeed barred from that seductive path into the darkness."

"Thank you," said Harry fervently.

"As to the wards," said Dumbledore, "I shall undertake a thorough review as soon as I am able. I shall bear your suggestions in mind, and implement as many as are reasonable."

Harry stared at him.

"Roughly what sort of timescale are we talking about here, Headmaster?"

"Perhaps a few months for the initial assessment, a few months to plan the upgrades, and a week or two to actually carry out the changes."

Harry took a half-step forward.

"Headmaster, people will die! Remember, Draco very nearly did die - that's why we're here. I don't want any of my classmates to die."

"You exaggerate, Mr Potter. I shall excuse it as a failing of youth, but you really ought to restrain yourself."

Hermione laid a hand on Harry's shoulder, and he subsided.

"Professor Dumbledore," said Hermione, "could I be involved in that? I don't suppose I'll be able to add much as a first-year, but this is a priceless opportunity for me to see exactly how serious wards are set up. Er, and from the look he's giving me I think Harry wants the same."

The Headmaster paused, and for several seconds he even closed his eyes. When his eyes opened, his face showed the full strain of his responsibilities.

"Miss Granger, above all else I must protect this world. You wield power already, and in time I suspect you will wield a great deal more. Will you first make an Unbreakable Vow to never abandon the Light?"

"Of course, Professor."

Dumbledore's wand was suddenly in his hand, without Harry or Hermione having seen him move to draw it. He turned and strode to the fireplace, igniting it with a twitch of his wand and tossing in a pinch of green powder from a bowl on the mantel. "Head of Ravenclaw office," he said rapidly but precisely, and a moment later his head had disappeared into the flames. Harry, meanwhile, was suddenly reminded of just how powerful and competent the Headmaster really was with magic. He repeated to himself his initial assessment, from the Welcoming Feast a lifetime ago: "Don't mess with Dumbledore."

A moment later Dumbledore withdrew his head from the fire, returning to his desk as if nothing had happened. Another moment, and Filius Flitwick emerged from the fire with the same graceful twirl that Harry remembered from McGonagall's office. Hermione, who was seeing it for the first time, looked at her Head of House with increased respect (which was saying something, this being Hermione).

"Filius," said Dumbledore, "I have agreed to upgrade our wards. Miss Granger wishes to be involved in the process, and I wish from her an Unbreakable Vow for security. Will you act as Bonder?"

Filius glanced at Hermione for confirmation, and then nodded. Dumbledore knelt, and motioned Hermione to do likewise. He took her hand in his, and then Flitwick's wand rested on their joined hands as Dumbledore began to speak very carefully.

"Will you, Hermione, remain always on the side of Light?"

"I will."

A thin tongue of brilliant flame sprang from Flitwick's wand and wound its way around their hands like a red-hot wire.

"Will you always guard any knowledge you gain about the wards of Hogwarts, and never divulge it to others or use it against Hogwarts?"

"I will."

A somewhat thicker tongue of flame leapt from Flitwick's wand, interweaving itself with the first.

"So be it."

The flames tightened around their joined hands, leaving thin red welts behind as they sank into the skin and vanished.

Hermione stood up, but Dumbledore remained kneeling.

"Harry, are you willing to make a Vow also? I will ask only that you not act against Hermione's wishes in significant matters of conscience."

Harry caught himself flinching away from making the commitment, and brutally overrode that flinch - all he was doing here was formalising the promise he had already made to Hermione, and even a brief hesitation at this point could carry significant costs. He knelt down and took Dumbledore's hand.

"Will you, Harry, always be bound by Hermione's morality in major matters of conscience?"

"I will."

As before, a thin tongue of flame from Flitwick's wand.

"So be it," said Dumbledore, a look of profound relief on his ancient and careworn face.

Harry winced slightly as the flames cut into his hand, but smiled beatifically nonetheless.

Chapter 10: Morality, Pt 2

Even deep in the peace of the phoenix, Hermione's mind was skittering and scrambling. Her moral certainty was crumbling within her, her whole self-concept was in question, and before Bentham started singing she'd been in more pain than ever before except for the trial (and that really shouldn't count). So here, at what was obviously a major turning point in her life, why on earth was her stupid brain determined to think about boys? Well, a boy, anyway. She knew all about priorities, for crying out loud - she was always really good at that - but somehow it just didn't work here. She gave a sort of a mental shrug and went with it, thankful to Bentham for making this so much easier than it might have been.

In the abstract, it was obvious that Harry was the only boy for her. She'd been sure almost since she met him that it was him or no one, though the "no one" option still couldn't be ruled out - after all, that had been her apparent fate until she met Harry. She hadn't even been sure she would ever have proper friends, let alone a boyfriend. Now she was suddenly very sure that she wanted Harry as a boyfriend, but that really didn't help - it just meant that instead of worrying about what she really wanted, she was now terrified about what Harry might or might not want. These feelings (and the awkward physical aspects of puberty) were so new to her, and Harry was nearly a year younger than her - was he even physically capable of feeling this way about her? Maybe he wasn't yet, and by saying something now she'd spook him and drive him away and lose her chance for when he did get to that point. Maybe he was, but he just didn't see her that way - maybe to him she was just the sister he never had, and he wanted someone else completely, someone sweet and meek like Hannah Abbott. No, that didn't make sense. But maybe he wanted someone who was older and knew more. Maybe he wanted a warrior noble like Tracey or Daphne, or a girl with mysterious superpowers like Susan, or even a sparkling socialite like Lavender or Parvati. Maybe he didn't want anyone at all and he never would, not like that. Maybe he liked boys. She had no idea, no way of knowing, and yet she needed to know.

Realistically, she knew she had a better chance than anyone else. If he was interested in romance at all yet, and if he liked girls, then she was probably his first choice. But that suddenly didn't seem like a very solid hope. She was suddenly painfully aware of just how much Harry really meant to her, and how much she probably meant to him. The Cloak, for a start - would he really have just handed that over to anyone else? And now the Vow - she knew he only gave it to get concessions from Dumbledore, but the fact remained that he had magically bound himself to her in a way that even married couples weren't bound. She was starting to realise how important Harry was likely to be to the world in general, Wizarding and non-Wizarding, and this could seriously damage that. Forget about her own feelings - what if she drove him away by saying the wrong thing or wanting the wrong thing, and then because of that he couldn't do what he had to do, and so the world suffered? Her stupid hormones could doom the world!

An amused smile flitted across her face, unseen, and she wrenched her thoughts back to the realms of the plausible and commonsensical. Harry might or might not be ready for such things, and he might or might not choose her when he was ready, but the worst she could really do by asking would be to cause a bit of awkwardness that they'd have to deal with. He couldn't decide he didn't even want her as a friend anymore - he was too deeply committed to her for that, even without the Vow. And they could always talk, and sort things out that way - she'd confirmed that to herself after the incident with those idiot Ravenclaw upper-years and their nonsensical ideas about romance. One way or another, it would be alright. She turned resolutely towards Harry to get all this off her chest.

Harry, meanwhile, had conflict enough swirling in his own head. He'd never been much for physical contact, no matter what McGonagall had said in Diagon Alley, but this physical closeness with Hermione felt unexpectedly pleasant and comfortable. As usual when surprised by anything, his first impulse was to update the expectations which had failed to predict this. His second impulse, close on the heels of the first, was to assert priorities and shut down any romantic thoughts: his best-and-possibly-only friend was in the middle of a painful and highly significant moral crisis, and he couldn't let himself be distracted by trivial things. Besides, he wasn't physically old enough to actually be having those sorts of feelings - he must just be imagining them, based on what his reading had led him to expect. With that settled, he turned his attention to the issue at hand.

Harry had studied moral philosophy, at least somewhat. He had, at least in theory, settled on preference utilitarianism - loosely speaking, satisfying the preferences of as many moral agents as possible. Even before he switched to that from his earlier and more naive position of hedonic utilitarianism, which in retrospect bore a worrying resemblance to Grindelwald's "Greater Good", Harry had realised that for practical purposes he really had to have cached rules by which to live his daily life. Now, of course, he was gradually coming to realise the extent to which most of his choices in daily life were actually driven by instinct and emotion rather than those rules anyway, but he knew he wasn't yet ready to deal with that properly. No matter. All of this tumbled through his head, coupled with the horrified realisation of just what Hermione must be going through. What for him had been a process of incremental realisation and refinement over a period of years, for her was being compressed into a single, world-smashing, moral crisis. She had thought a lot about doing the right thing, he knew, and had even recently given some thought to which rules were best, but to his knowledge she had never seriously considered the possibility that a rigid set of rules might not be the best approach to morality. She had even thought that he was going evil, just because he didn't follow her rule-based approach to morality. Admittedly she'd been right about that, but not for the reason she'd thought.

Harry gazed blankly at the stone floor in front of his feet, letting himself feel the full torment of Hermione's position as he imagined it.

Finally he felt Hermione move, and he turned to her as she turned to him. He opened his mouth to speak, not even sure what to say, but she spoke first.

"Harry, do you like me?"

This he could deal with. "Hermione, of course I like you. You're the most moral person I know."

She paused for a moment, then ploughed on. "Um... That's... not quite what I meant. Harry... You're my best friend. You're my first friend. I think we're probably going to save the world together, one of these days. I... I just need you to know that... That you're more than a friend to me. Um... I don't know how you feel, I don't even know whether you're old enough to care about that sort of thing, and even if you are I don't know if you're even into girls at all rather than boys, and for all I know you could be in love with Tracey Davis or anyone, and I don't know, and I know I'm making an idiot of myself, and... Well, I had to tell you. Please don't hate me?"

Harry stared at her, mouth hanging open slightly. Long moments passed in awkward, terrified silence. Finally he spoke.

"Um... Hermione. Just warning you up front, I have no idea how to deal with this. I am a very long way out of my depth right now, so please forgive me if any of this comes out wrong. I, um. First, to be clear, I do like you. You're my best friend, my first friend, and quite possibly still my only real friend. No matter what happens, I definitely want you around. I mean, I just swore an Unbreakable Vow binding me to your moral judgement. We're sitting here right now in my brand-new still-under-construction secret hideaway, which is and will remain a complete secret from absolutely everyone who is not currently sitting here. Um... So, yeah, I trust you more than I have ever trusted anyone else. I trust you completely, in a way that I never thought I would trust anyone at all."

Harry paused, but Hermione said nothing. After a few moments, he went on.

"As for the other thing... Hermione, I'm eleven years old. I know you're a bit older than me, and maybe you've gone through some changes that I haven't, but I shouldn't be physically capable of falling in love yet. That being said, if I could right now, I think it would definitely be you. I mean, I know all this stuff about how I couldn't possibly really be feeling these things yet, but I guess I shouldn't underestimate my imagination, because I really do feel like I imagine I would if I actually were old enough, and if I actually were falling in love with you. Um."

There was another silence, since even at only twelve years of age Hermione was smart enough to keep her mouth shut and just let Harry talk himself around - not for nothing was she the brightest witch of her generation. Eventually Harry went on.

"I mean, I don't actually think girls are icky, but then I never really did see the point of that - people are just people, and I try to appreciate the ones who are less stupid than the rest. I still don't see the point of kissing, I honestly don't - it just seems awkward and messy - but I think I've finally realised how good hugs are. Um... I think that might count as me growing up? Maybe? I don't know. I'm definitely in favour of hugs now, though, at least with you. Um... So I don't know what that makes us, but I think there is an 'us'. I don't think anyone would take us seriously as boyfriend and girlfriend anyway, not at our age, so we're probably better off not saying anything about it. But I'm fine with us thinking of ourselves that way, if you like - it's not as if there's anyone else I'm interested in like this.

"Um... Am I making any sense? Am I just getting myself into trouble here? I really hadn't given this any thought, so this is all completely off the top of my head, and I know I don't always do very well with that."

Hermione snuggled into him, secure once more. "I think everything's OK."

Harry let out a breath he hadn't known he was holding, feeling the tension leave his shoulders - Bentham was wonderful, and Harry wasn't at all sure he could have managed this without phoenix calm, but apparently there were limits even there.

After a long and much more comfortable silence, Bentham opened his wings and flew across the cavern. Harry reluctantly disentangled himself from Hermione and stood up, reaching down to help her up before stretching after so long on cold stone.

Hermione, once she'd done her own stretching, turned to Harry. "I think perhaps I should sleep on those moral questions - they're just a bit too much right now. Can we talk about something else now, and talk about this tomorrow instead?"

"Of course we can - I know this isn't easy for you. I had years to work through the stuff that's pretty much all being dumped on you right now, and even for me it wasn't always easy."

Hermione hugged Harry in thanks, reveling in the sheer novelty of the physical contact. "So what now?"

He glanced at his watch, and grinned. "We have quite a bit of time up our sleeves - actually, our earlier selves are on the other side of that wall right now. Anyway, we've got about an hour before we have to go back. Do you want to work on this place? It's going to take a while, but I want it to be a comfortable place to live long-term if necessary. I also want it to be as secure as we can make it. I'm already planning another hideout that we'll make in the future, one that'll be much more secure even than this, but this one's important for now, plus it'll teach us everything we need to know for the longer-term one. And, y'know, it can't hurt to have a spare."

"You mean this place is a practice piece?"

Harry grinned. "Among other things, yes. So, Miss Brightest-Witch-Of-Her-Generation, tell me what it needs and how we're going to make it all happen."

Hermione was caught flat-footed for a moment, but only a moment, before her all-conquering brain kicked into gear - if Harry wanted her to design him a hideout, then she'd design him a hideout. And what's more, she'd design a hideout that she wouldn't mind living in for a long time herself - maybe it was Harry's pessimism-as-a-virtue finally affecting her, but she suspected she'd be spending a lot of time here.

"Well, for a start we'll need a permanent Air-Freshening charm. We're safe for now, it takes a long time to use up all the air in a space this big, but in the end we'd suffocate and die. We'll need a better light, too - my Lumos Maxima won't last forever, and we'll want to be able to turn the light on and off anyway. We're wasting a lot of space with this ridiculously high ceiling, so we'll probably want to split it into two levels, or maybe even three. Can you do that with the same trick you used to pull out the chunks of stone in the first place? If you just isolate the layer of stone under our feet, and get Bentham's help to lift it up and anchor it about halfway up... That transfiguration will do that, won't it? Oh, and we'll need to strengthen the stone when we do that, or it might break. Um... We'll want water, and we don't want to have to keep using Aguamenti - I think we can do that with runes, but I'll have to look it up. I'll have to look up a lot of things. Um... We'll also want a toilet, if we're going to spend much time here. Aguamenti runes and vanishing runes should work for that. Actually I don't know why Hogwarts doesn't do it like that - according to Hogwarts: A History, the toilets flush into the Lake!"

Harry, well aware of modern sanitation and its importance, looked appropriately horrified. Hermione went on.

"But honestly, Harry, we're going to have to plan this properly - we can't just dive in and start building it, and expect to end up with anything like what we actually wanted. We can't make what we want until we figure out what that is. We need pen and paper and time to brainstorm together."

Harry looked slightly embarrassed. "To be fair, we did need to get as far as having a private place to plan the rest."

Hermione nodded, and went on.

"So I'll think up ideas for this, but then we need to make a proper plan before we actually do anything. Are we clear?"

Harry nodded, eyes somewhat wild. "Agreed."

"Good. Now, we'll need internal walls of some sort - we can probably just use stone for those. That might even make the ceiling safe without magic, though we'd strengthen it anyway."

Harry nodded again, not quite daring to speak. Hermione continued, warming to her theme.

"The whole cube is what, eight metres? Ten? I say we put all our living spaces on the bottom level, and two metres is plenty of height for that. Leave the rest as a big space for training or whatever - we can add things later if we want to."

Hermione became aware that Harry was staring at her in something akin to awe.

"Hermione," he said, "did I ever tell you you're amazing? I was expecting a few clever ideas that I could then use in the plan that I was going to make for this place, but you actually know what you're talking about! Um... Sorry, I didn't mean it like that. But I'll help you plan this, not the other way around. I knew you were brilliant, I knew about your ridiculously good memory, and I knew you'd had perfect marks in basically everything you've ever studied, but how on Earth do you know so much about engineering and architecture?"

Hermione smiled beatifically. "I didn't always live in the house that you visited, you know. Mum and Dad built that house, or at least they designed it with an architect and had it built. I was six, and much too cute for anyone to tell me I couldn't listen to all the planning. I ended up talking quite a lot to the architect and the engineer, and also some of the builders. I also went and read some books, because I was curious."

Harry shook his head slowly. "You read some books. You read some books. I am so glad you're on my side."

Harry pulled pens and a sheaf of paper from his mokeskin pouch - God he loved that pouch! - and he and Hermione settled down to scribble plans together. It'd all have to stay in the cube, of course - people would obviously be suspicious if they saw any of this - but this way they could hash out their ideas much more clearly and easily than trying to express everything in spoken words.

By the time Harry's watch jangled to remind them to go, they were both sprawled on the floor surrounded by loose sheets of paper covered with assorted half-formed scribbles - they were mostly just passing ideas back and forth, so anyone else looking at those papers would have struggled to understand much.

Just before they left, however, Hermione turned to Harry with a sad but determined look on her face. "I think you're right. I think we have to kill Professor Quirrell."

Harry nodded and put a reassuring hand on her shoulder, and Bentham flamed the pair of them to the Great Hall for dinner.

Chapter 13: Also Allowed to be Smart

A/N: Finally figured what should happen next, so I've come back to this story. CW: character death.

Safely back in their secret hideaway, Harry and Hermione stood in silence for a time.

Finally Hermione drew in a deep breath and then released it slowly, tremblingly. Her lips twisted into an unaccustomed bitter half-grimace, half-smile.
"Well, you were definitely right about killing Professor Quirrell. Pity we can't actually touch him, though."

Harry nodded slowly, looking more tired than anything else.
"Yeah. Pity, that. Honestly, I'm just glad we're still alive."

Hermione tilted her head to the side slightly, opened her mouth to answer him. Suddenly, abruptly, her eyes widened. Her face twisted as she gave a gasping sort of half-cry. Her whole body shuddered violently, just once, before dropping bonelessly to the floor.

Harry stared in uncomprehending horror for a split-second, but a moment later he was running forward with his magical first-aid kit already halfway out of his pouch. He pressed two fingers against her throat, desperately hoping for a pulse.

Nothing.

Her skin felt oddly swollen, and slick with sweat that he was sure hadn't been there a moment before. As he drew his fingers away, he noticed an uncomfortable tingling sensation in his fingertips. He held a fingertip to his nose, and sniffed cautiously.

Faint but clear, a sharp smell like dilute vinegar.

The answer seemed to drop into Harry's mind fully-formed, terrible and unarguable. Some quantity of a strong acid, Transfigured into a tiny ice chip or something and then just flicked into Hermione's mouth when her attention was elsewhere. Several hours for that Transfigured substance to circulate and diffuse through her body, until finally the Transfiguration wore off. Whatever quantity of acid, suddenly appearing distributed throughout her body - hence the swelling, the sharp sweat, and of course the near-instant shutdown of her body.

Idiot. Complete, absolute, idiot. Harry had thought of this exact attack, had considered using it himself. He had even spent time trying to think of antidotes, and failed. And yet he hadn't thought to defend against what was in retrospect a fairly obvious threat. And now Hermione was - his brain refused to think it. It fought against years of conditioning, and flinched away from the painful thought. Too painful. No.

He felt his dark side rising, but it too was utterly inadequate to a grief like this. Instead he became simply Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres, but a Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres with nothing of softness or compromise in him. This was his intent-to-kill, his full problem-solving abilities unleashed with no censors whatsoever.

Right. Someone had died. Actually died. No more Batman code. Time to just end this, as quickly as possible. No filters, no censors, just get the job done.

But then, this was Professor Quirrell. How could he possibly take down Professor Quirrell? For that matter, how could he even find him?

Oh, right. Bentham. First problem solved.

How to actually get a shot at Quirrell? Good question. No spell, because Quirrell was just too fast. Actually, he'd need to be completely undetectable in order to have any chance. Right, the Cloak.

What attack? No offensive spell, of course. Transfiguration? High explosives? Muggle explosives didn't really seem up to the task, somehow. It'd have to be something that Professor Quirrell didn't know about.

Antimatter? Harry had thought about this a few times in the past, but had realised quite rapidly that it was a lot less simple than people thought. Antimatter wasn't just this one kind of stuff with the property goes-boom. It was a reflection, an inversion, of normal matter, with all the complexity of that. It would only annihilate neatly if it encountered the exact right kind of normal matter.

Up quarks? Harry wasn't at all sure that that would work, and he also wasn't sure what would happen if it did work. So, no.

Electrons? Low mass, but so tiny that they'd be seriously dense if you packed them tightly. Physics couldn't do that, but Transfiguration could. A cubic centimetre of electrons, densely packed, should have plenty of energy to destroy Professor Quirrell. And Harry himself, of course, but at this point that was simply a necessary sacrifice. Professor Quirrell was now an obvious existential threat to humanity, and Harry was humanity's only hope. Harry was vaguely aware that this explosion would also kill some number of innocent bystanders, but that concern belonged in the world of comic-book heroes. In context of an existential threat to the entire human race, it was regrettable but still ultimately inconsequential that some number of innocent people must die.

Now, the repulsive force between electrons grows more than linearly with respect to both the number of electrons and their closeness to one another. This was a fact known to Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres at this time, at least in theory. It did not occur to him. Instead, just this once, he did the normal human thing; he simply assumed that a cubic centimetre of something non-exotic, no matter what that substance might be, could not actually pose a threat to humanity simply by existing. And electrons were hardly exotic - after all, humans had many whole industries based around manipulating electrons very cleverly.

There was no reason to suppose that Professor Quirrell would destroy humanity immediately, nor even that he would immediately take effective steps to defend himself against discovery by phoenix (if indeed such a defence were even possible). This, too, Harry completely failed to think about.

There also existed many other compelling arguments against taking immediate drastic action. Precisely none of those arguments occurred to Harry; precisely none was allowed to occur to him. Reason was indeed the slave of the passions - Hume had been right about that - and Harry's emotional reality was at this moment still consumed by unthinkable loss.

Harry turned to Bentham, held out a hand. The bird flicked onto the boy's wrist, silent. Harry swirled the Cloak around them both and then thought of Professor Quirrell; a moment later the hideout stood empty.

The first thing Harry noticed was a sense of doom. Extremely faint, but it was there. Idiot! He really, really should have thought of that.

Quirrell was both inactive and asleep - of course, that performance in the Great Hall would have tired him significantly. He was sprawled haphazardly on a bed, diagonally opposite Harry in a fairly large room. There was very little light, and no sign of other people; that was all Harry bothered to notice before focusing on the problem at hand. He might not have much time, before Professor Quirrell might feel the sense of doom and wake up. That could not be allowed to happen.

Harry stared at his ice cube and concentrated on his Transfiguration, articulating inside his head:
"One cubic centimetre of electrons, packed as tightly as possible."

An unfamiliar Transfiguration, but not intrinsically a very difficult one. Not for Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres. It was done in a matter of seconds.

A sense of satisfaction approached Harry's mind as he felt the Transfiguration beginning to complete, and that was the last he knew.

At the tip of Harry's wand, a cubic centimetre of ice became (very briefly) a cubic centimetre of densely-packed electrons. Magic didn't care about conservation of mass-energy, so Harry had not in fact encountered any difficulty Transfiguring a gram of ice into approximately one seventieth the mass of the Moon in electrons. He had merely Transfigured a cubic centimetre of one substance into a cubic centimetre of another substance, and Magic didn't care if the mass had increased by twenty orders of magnitude.

That mass would have severely inconvenienced a great many people, except that it was completely irrelevant beside the total electrical charge on those electrons. Electrons are negatively charged, and therefore they repel each other. Harry had inadvertently concentrated a ridiculous number of electrons in rather a small space, and those electrons therefore proceeded to repel each other with correspondingly ridiculous vigour.

Harry himself simply ceased to exist in any meaningful physical sense, as did his Cloak and everything else that he was carrying. The grief-stricken Harry-in-the-moment had achieved his desired self-destruction, far more effectively than he had ever imagined.

Professor Quirrell's body was likewise utterly unmade within the briefest of instants, as was the room itself.

Within one tenth of a millisecond, the entire city had essentially dissolved.

Another tenth of a millisecond, and the blast radius had reached through the Earth's crust and touched the mantle.

Several hundred kilometres overhead, the Russian space station Mir received approximately two milliseconds of light from the ongoing destruction, before it too was destroyed by the expanding shell of extremely energetic electrons. The two cosmonauts on board knew nothing of this in any case; it was night time in Moscow, and Mir's windows were therefore covered. Four milliseconds had now elapsed since Harry completed his Transfiguration.

Even with a destructive wavefront propagating outwards at half the speed of light, things still take time. The Earth's destruction took eighty-five milliseconds.

The Moon outlived Harry and Professor Quirrell by only a few seconds.

As it happened, Mercury was the nearest extraterrestrial planet; it disappeared a little over ten minutes later.

Another six minutes later, the late Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres did indeed begin to "tear apart the very stars in heaven". The expanding shell of electrons swept the Sun away almost contemptuously, or would have done if emotions applied to simple physics. Even at a radius of a hundred and fifty million kilometres, the electrons still carried more than enough energy density to overpower the star's binding energy. By quite some orders of magnitude still, if truth be told.

In the next twenty minutes, Venus and then Mars were unmade. Each died in darkness, the sun's last rays having outpaced the avenging electrons.

In the end, the local stellar neighborhood at least was saved by a fact that the late Minerva McGonagall had impressed upon generations of students: Transfiguration is not permanent. Somewhere around half a billion kilometres from Earth, that dreadful shell of electrons suddenly reverted to ice.

That initial gram of ice was now spread out around the inner solar system, so for all practical purposes it simply disappeared.

Jupiter, the star that never was, escaped destruction by a quarter-hour.

Three billion kilometres past Jupiter's orbit, a golden plaque drifted peacefully among the stars. Within it lay the last remnant of the man once called Quirrell. Far behind it lay the wreckage of the inner solar system, the last remnant of Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres and his uniquely destructive genius.

Fin.

A/N: This outcome is basically why Quirrell suddenly regards Harry as an existential threat after Hermione's death in HPMOR, and yeah EY was aware of the Transfiguring-electrons idea when he wrote that. I took some ideas and formulas from discussions in several different subreddits, but in the end I did do all the math myself. A cc of densely-packed electrons would contain roughly 1e70 joules of Coulomb energy, which is completely ridiculous. I did calculate how long the electrons would take to reach things (assuming 0.5c speed), including looking up all the actual distances as at April 6th 1992 (except for the plaque which I had to calculate for myself). And yeah that shell of electrons absolutely would tear other stars apart if the Transfiguration lasted long enough. Oh, and I'm assuming that the packing isn't quite enough to bring the strong nuclear force into play. I am not remotely qualified to talk about what would happen in that case.

I know that this ending is weird and kinda unsatisfying, but I think it makes sense for a meta-fanfic like this one. We already have HPMOR itself as a story that follows narrative conventions, which leaves this story free to explore the entirely realistic prospect of sudden catastrophic failure. I didn't make anyone act uncharacteristically in order to bring this about, and I didn't use anything that wasn't already available in the story (except for Transfiguring electrons instead of up quarks like Harry originally wondered about).

Sincerest thanks to my beta reader AnimeKitty47, and to everyone else who reviewed this story. This was my first attempt at writing fanfiction, for that matter it was my first substantial attempt at writing fiction of any kind, and honestly I'm just so glad I finished it in the end.

-Pat